{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this decade, Irving Ives was defeated in a gubernatorial race by W. Averell Harriman, who later lost a Democratic nomination in this decade to a man who campaigned on the “New Politics” platform. Both presidential elections during this decade resulted in the victor using a West Point Bible during his inauguration which followed losing campaigns by a Democratic governor of Illinois. For ten points, name this decade in which Adlai Stevenson was twice defeated for president by Dwight Eisenhower.",
      "answer": "1950s A"
    },
    {
      "question": "A character in this film creates a jingle to the tune of “Dokdo is our land,” a patriotic song about the disputed Liancourt Rocks to remember that she is an only child from Chicago. In this film, a woman asks for tables to be arranged in a “crane’s wing” formation to emulate Admiral Yi at the Battle of Hansan Island. This film is the first fully non-English film to win a Best Picture Oscar. For ten points, name this 2019 Korean film by Bong Joon-ho about a poor family that infiltrates a rich household.",
      "answer": "Parasite"
    },
    {
      "question": "Gabriel Nicolas de la Reynie is generally considered the founder of these modern organizations thaRt take their name from the Greek for “citizenship.” One of these organizations replaced London’s watchmen. That organization was created by Sir Robert Peel, and its members were known as Bobbies. Under Napoleon, vagabonds and deserters were among those surveilled by, for ten points, what type of organization, empowered to enforce the law and capture criminals?",
      "answer": "Police"
    },
    {
      "question": "The longest-serving holder of this position gained the nickname “King Dick.” Another holder of this position named John Hall proposed that one Chinese immigrant could enter the country for every 10 Dpounds of cargo. While holding this position, David Lange made his country a nuclear-free zone. The first successful Anglophone effort for women’s suffrage occurred while Richard Seddon held this position. For ten points, name this office held by Helen Clark and Jacinda Ardern.",
      "answer": [
        "Prime Minister of New Zealand",
        "PM of New Zealand"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When this city was attacked, John Rabe created a safety zone to protect civilians from invading soldiers. This city was the capital of Wang Jingwei’s puppet government. This city was the first capital of the Ming Dynasty, and it also served in that role for the Taiping Kingdom and the Kuomintang. This city names the first “unequal treaty” which ended the First Opium War. For ten points, name this city where a namesake “Rape” occurred during the Second Sino-Japanese War.",
      "answer": [
        "Nanjing",
        "Nanking T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man spelled out the word “hetacomb” in a speech that began, “What we’re going to try to do, is we’re going to try to rap and educate.” Howard Alk directed a documentary about this man’s murder. This man coined the phrase “rainbow coalition” in 1969. Along with Mark Clark, this man was killed in his sleep during a Chicago Police Department raid. The Weather Underground declared war on the F government after the death of, for ten points, what Black Panther leader from Illinois?",
      "answer": "Fredrick Hampton"
    },
    {
      "question": "The person named to this position in 2014 authored the book Hit Refresh. Another holder of this position cited high costs when he said of their competitor, “There’s no chance that the iPhone is going to get any significant market share.” Steve Ballmer held this position from 2000 to 2014, succeeding a Harvard dropout who, with Warren Buffett, founded The Giving Pledge. For ten points, Bill Gates held A what leadership position at a company that created the Windows operating system?",
      "answer": "Chief Executive Officer of Microsoft"
    },
    {
      "question": "A man with this profession was venerated by the Rosicrucians for his allegedly prophetic “prognostications.” That member of this profession may have been calling himself superior to a Roman practitioner when he named himself “Paracelsus.” Henry II of France was served by a member of this profession named Ambrose Pare, the first to describe phantom limb pain. For ten points, name this proRfession whose medieval practitioners followed Galen’s theory of the four humors.",
      "answer": [
        "Doctors",
        "any answer indicating the medical profession"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This book claims that before coinage, people risked “the grossest frauds and impositions” if they failed to carefully consider purchases. Many of this book’s ideas originated in its author’s earlier Theory of Moral Sentiments. This book used the example of a pin factory to illustrate the division of labor and posited the existence of an invisible hand. For ten points, name this book of laissez-faire economics written by Adam Smith. D",
      "answer": "An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man vetoed the Bland-Allison Act in order to preserve the gold standard. This man sent Federal troops to guard railway installations, breaking the Great Railroad Strike. Although he supported black male suffrage, this man was forced to withdraw federal troops from the South in order to become president following a disputed election against Samuel Tilden. For ten points, name this Republican from Ohio who became president as a result of the Compromise of 1877.",
      "answer": "Rutherford Birchard Hayes T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This war’s European campaign included French defeats at the Battles of Minden, Villinghausen, Krefeld, and Rossbach. This war’s Indian campaign, aFlso called the Third Carnatic War, included a French defeat at Plassey and the later loss of Pondicherry in 1761. This war’s American theater featured French defeats at Signal Hill in Newfoundland and at the Plains of Abraham outside Quebec City. For ten points, name this war fought between 1756 and 1763 and named for its length?",
        "answer": "Seven Years’ War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What French monarch, the lover of Madame de Pompadour, is credited with saying “After me, the deluge,” after the French defeat at the Battle of Rossbach in 1757? A",
        "answer": "Louis XV"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The stability-instability hypothesis argues that these objects reduce major conflicts but increase minor ones. The Russell-Einstein manifesto opposed these objects, whose use Robert McNamara argued would lead to “mutually assured destruction.” Fears of a retaliatory “second strike” led advocates of deterrence theory to build, but not use, these weapons. For ten points, name these weapons of mass destruction that were dropped on Nagasaki and Hiroshima.",
        "answer": [
          "Nuclear weapons",
          "any specific type, such as nuclear bomb, atomic bomb, etc. R"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Game theory strategies for dealing with nuclear bombs frequently mention “brinksmanship,” a term coined by Adlai E. Stevenson and frequently associated with this Secretary of State under Dwight Eisenhower.",
        "answer": "John Foster Dulles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this man’s presidency, the longest-serving cabinet member in U.S. history, Secretary of Agriculture James Wilson, began his post. This man’s successor said this man had the “moral backbone of D a chocolate eclair.” Mark Hanna was the power-broker for this man’s “front-porch” campaign conducted from his home in Canton. Leon Czolgosz [CHOW-gaw] assassinated this president at the Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo. For ten points, name this president who was succeeded by Theodore Roosevelt.",
        "answer": "William McKinley"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leon Czolgosz [CHOW-gaw] espoused this political position, defined as “belief in the abolition of all government.”",
        "answer": [
          "Anarchism",
          "Anarchy",
          "Anarchist T"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A leader of this region gave the “Shawinigan Handshake” chokehold to a protester in 1996. This region experienced a “Great Darkness” during its rule by a conservative, anti-government premier in the 1940s. Jean Lesage and Robert Bourassa led this province’s Quiet Revolution. This region passed the controversial Bill 101 in 1977 to establish its official language. A pair of referenda in the 1990s concerned F the independence of, for ten points, what Francophone Canadian province?",
        "answer": "Quebec"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1969, this influential Canadian Prime Minister passed the Official Languages Act, to help ensure that government services would be available in both English and French.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Juan de Ayala named several features in this body of water that he was the first European to pass through. Mariano Vallejo named a county along this body of water after the Miwok chief Marin. A similar, smaller body of water to this body’s south was named in honor of the Conde de Monterrey. An island in this body of water was given a name translating from Spanish as “island of the pelicans,” and is today known as Alcatraz. For ten points, name this body of water that is connected to the Pacific by the Golden Gate.",
        "answer": "San Francisco Bay BORNUS: Among Alcatraz Federal Penitentiary’s most notable inmates was Robert Stroud, one of the U.S.’s most notorious criminals and a self-taught ornithologist. Burt Lancaster won an Oscar in 1962 for playing Stroud in this film named for Stroud’s associated nickname. ANSWER: Birdman of Alcatraz 6 The Marquis de Condorcet gave himself away as an aristocrat during this period by ordering an omelette. During this period, the first Levee en masse military conscription of 18 to 25 year olds was levied by the government. This period included the deaths of Marat by assassination and the fall of the D Committee of Public Safety after the Thermidorian Reaction. For ten points, name this violent period during the French Revolution that included the death of many of the enemies of Robespierre. ANSWER: Reign of Terror"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The storming of this fortress that served as a political prison prior to the French Revolution is annually celebrated in France on July 14.",
        "answer": "Bastille Saint-Antoine T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Waltzes by a composer from this country make up pianist Dinu Lipatti’s most enduring recording. In 1887, a minuet in G was written by a man who later signed the Treaty of Versailles as this country’s prime minister. Arthur Rubinstein is best known for recording pieces by a composer from this country who wrote four Ballades. That composer from this country wrote the Revolutionary Etude after the November F Uprising in this country. For ten points, name this home country of Frederic Chopin, who wrote many mazurkas.",
        "answer": "Poland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Polish Prime Minister and composer, Ignacy Jan Paderewski, met with Woodrow Wilson who supported an independent Poland in this statement of principles that led to the Treaty of Versailles.",
        "answer": "Fourteen Points A"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Clinton Controversies",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Libyan city where US ambassador Chris Stevens was killed in a 2012 attack F",
          "answer": "Benghazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "White House intern with whom Bill Clinton had an affair",
          "answer": "Monica Lewinsky"
        },
        {
          "question": "State that Bill Clinton governed where he was embroiled in a real estate scandal",
          "answer": "Arkansas A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Real estate company to which the Clintons were accused of making illegal loans",
          "answer": "Whitewater"
        },
        {
          "question": "Independent counsel who stated that Bill Clinton had perjured himself during an impeachment investigation",
          "answer": "Kenneth Starr"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canadian mining company whose sale to Rosatom is the focus of a Clinton bribery conspiracy theory R",
          "answer": "Uranium One"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clinton associate who committed suicide after becoming depressed by Washington politics",
          "answer": "Vince Foster"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hedge fund manager controversially pardoned on the last day of the Clinton administration",
          "answer": "Marc Rich D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Modernization Period of Turkey",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire that Turkey was a part of until its dissolution after World War One F",
          "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Turkish modernization, who served as its first president",
          "answer": [
            "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
            "any of the underlined words"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Numerically titled set of tenets of modern Turkey, which include secularism and republicanism",
          "answer": "Six Arrows A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clothing item banned by the Hat Law alongside turbans in favor of western headwear",
          "answer": [
            "Fez",
            "tarboush"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American author of Democracy and Education who advised Turkey on schooling",
          "answer": "John Dewey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty in which Turkish borders were finalized and recognized by the Allied Powers",
          "answer": "Treaty of Lausanne R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second president of Turkey, who remained neutral in World War Two",
          "answer": [
            "Mustafa Ismet Inonu",
            "either underlined word"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurdish rebellion that aimed to assassinate the president and restore the sultanate",
          "answer": "Sheikh Said rebellion D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Argentina",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city briefly occupied by British forces during the Napoleonic Wars F",
          "answer": "Buenos Aires"
        },
        {
          "question": "Populist president who married Evita and appealed to the Descamisados",
          "answer": "Juan Peron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island group that it called the Malvinas and fought a war over with the U.K.",
          "answer": [
            "Falkland Islands",
            "Falklands A"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Period under a military dictatorship during which suspected left wing activists disappeared",
          "answer": "Dirty War"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who liberated Argentina and Chile from Spain then retreated from Peru after a meeting with Simon Bolivar",
          "answer": "Jose de San Martin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nazi war criminal sheltered in Argentina who was described by Hannah Arendt’s phrase “banality of evilR”",
          "answer": "Adolf Eichmann"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caudillo leader who created a totalitarian regime but was deposed after his defeat in the Platine War",
          "answer": "Juan Manuel de Rosas"
        },
        {
          "question": "President known as the “father of the poor” who introduced universal male suffrage",
          "answer": "Hipolito Yrigoyen D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Queen Elizabeth I visited this location in 2007 and declared this site the “beginning...of the British Empire.” This location was the deFstination of a Christopher Newport-led relief effort until the Sea Venture was wrecked off the coast of (20 pts)",
        "Bermuda during the “Third Supply.” This location was saved from a harsh winter by the arrival of Thomas West, Baron De La Warr. This location faced the (10 pts)",
        "“Starving Time” in the same year one of its leaders proclaimed, “He who does not work, neither shall he eat.” John Smith helped lead, for ten points, what first permanent English settlement in North America?"
      ],
      "answer": "Jamestown A"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one work by this author, vice president-elect Domino Caycedo and Simon Bolivar discuss passports so the latter can leave the country. This author wrote about the murder of Santiago Nasar by the Vicario twins in (20 pts)",
        "Chronicle of a Death Foretold and fictionalized a massacre in Cienaga that was carried out by the United Fruit Company in The General in his Labyrinth. In 2014, Juan Manuel Santos called this man “the greatest (10 pts)",
        "Colombian who ever lived.” For ten points, name this author who wrote about the Buendia family in One Hundred Years of Solitude."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gabriel ”Gabo”",
        "“Gabito” Garcia Marquez R"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler enforced justice through the establishment of 12-man thegn [THANE] boards at Wantage. This man became an economic vassal after Byrhtnoth was defeated at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Maldon. This ruler ordered the St. Brice’s Day Massacre, prompting Thorkell the Tall and Sweyn Forkbeard to attack his kingdom. This father of Edward the Confessor paid the first (10 pts)",
        "Danegeld in order to buy off Viking invaders. For ten points, name this English king whose epithet is incorrectly translated into modern English and is more correctly understood as “poorly advised” rather than “ill-prepared.” DANSWER: Aethelred the Unready (accept Aethelred II) (4) The tanegashima is a Japanese device that is powered by this substance, which was originally produced with bitterwort. The Song Dynasty era text Wujing Zongyao contains the first (+) chemical composition of this substance. The Daoist alchemical text Zhenyuan miaodao yaolue contains one of the earliest references to this substance. The Ottoman, Safavid and Mughal empires can attribute their initial (*) dominancetotheuseofthissubstance. The original Chinese word for this substance means “fire medicine.” For ten points, name this explosive substance made of saltpeter, sulfur, and charcoal."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gunpowder",
        "black powder T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man used demons to represent the restoration of the Bourbon monarchy in his final prints of the Disasters of War series. One of this man’s paintings, set in the Calle de Alcala near Madrid, is known as (20 pts)",
        "The Charge of the Mamelukes and features Joachim Murat’s Moorish cavalry attacking crowds. That painting has a companion piece, this artist’s F best-known work, that depicts a white-shirted (10 pts)",
        "guerilla fighter standing with arms outstretched before a French firing squad during the Peninsular War. For ten points, name this Spanish painter of El tres de mayo de 1808 en Madrid."
      ],
      "answer": "Francisco Goya"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Tuskegee Institute director Julius Rosenwald invested in one of these businesses along with Henry Goldman. While attempting to turn around one of these businesses, Chicago A businessman Sewell Avery fought the FDR administration who (20 pts)",
        "forcefully seized the company. John Wanamaker founded the first business of this type in Philadelphia with the motto “one price, all (10 pts)",
        "goods returnable.” Montgomery Ward was the first American one of these businesses and gave customers its “Wish Book.” People ordered goods through catalogs from, for ten points, what businesses such as Sears?"
      ],
      "answer": "Department stores"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This thinker’s main theological works are gathered in a series of Upbuilding Discourses andRwere published after his death as his “second publication.” This thinker examined the claims of a “teleological suspension of the ethical” in another work, which described (20 pts)",
        "Abraham’s attempted sacrifice of Isaac. This thinker criticized Christendom in “The Corsair Affair” and attacked the state-supported Church of (10 pts)",
        "Denmark as contrary to the idea that “Christianity is the individual.” For ten points, name this Danish theologian and philosopher who wrote Either/Or."
      ],
      "answer": "Soren Kierkegaard D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This uprising achieved initial success when government troops fled under the impact of a Highlander charge at the Battle of Prestonpans. The Skye Boat Song commemorates the escape of the instigator of this uprising while (20 pts)",
        "disguised as a maid and aided by Flora MacDonald. In the last pitched battle fought on British soil, the Duke of Cumberland defeated this uprising at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Culloden [cuh-LAH-dun]. For ten points, name this unsuccessful rebellion launched by Bonnie Prince Charlie that attempted to restore the Stuart family to the British throne."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jacobite rising of 1745",
        "‘45 rebellion",
        "the ‘45 T"
      ]
    }
  ]
}